<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
/*
 * Copyright 2002-2010 the original author or authors.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
-->
<chapter xml:id="preface" xmlns="https://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>Developing software applications is hard enough even with good tools
  and technologies. Spring provides a light-weight solution for building
  enterprise-ready applications. Spring provides a consistent and transparent
  means to configure your application and integrate <link
  linkend="aop-introduction-concepts">AOP</link> into your software. Highlights of
  Spring's functionality are providing declarative transaction management for
  your middle tier as well as a full-featured ASP.NET framework.</para>

  <para>Spring could potentially be a one-stop-shop for many areas of
  enterprise application development; however, Spring is modular, allowing you
  to use just those parts of it that you need, without having to bring in the
  rest. You can use just the IoC container to configure your application and
  use traditional ADO.NET based data access code, but you could also choose to
  use just the <link linkend="orm">Hibernate integration code</link>
  or the <link linkend="ado-introduction">ADO.NET abstraction layer</link>.
  Spring has been (and continues to be) designed to be non-intrusive, meaning
  dependencies on the framework itself are generally none (or absolutely
  minimal, depending on the area of use).</para>

  <para>This document provides a reference guide to Spring's features. Since
  this document is still to be considered very much work-in-progress, if you
  have any requests or comments, please post them on the user mailing list or
  on the support forums at <ulink
  url="https://forum.springframework.net">forum.springframework.net</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Before we go on, a few words of gratitude are due to Christian Bauer
  (of the <ulink url="https://hibernate.org/">Hibernate</ulink> team), who
  prepared and adapted the DocBook-XSL software in order to be able to create
  Hibernate's reference guide, thus also allowing us to create this one. Also
  thanks to Russell Healy for doing an extensive and valuable review of some
  of the material.</para>
</chapter>