<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="web">
  <title>Spring.NET Web Framework</title>

  <sect1 id="web-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>One of the objections many developers have to the ASP.NET
    programming model is that it is not a "true MVC" (Model-View-Controller)
    implementation, because controller-type logic within the page is too
    tightly coupled to the view. A good example of this are event handlers
    within the page class, which typically have references to view elements,
    such as input controls, all over the place. Without getting into academic
    discussion of what "true MVC" is, and whether it is even appropriate to
    try to fit form-based technology such as ASP.NET into traditionally
    request-based MVC pattern when MVP (Model-View-Presenter) or Presentation
    Model might be more appropriate, we'd like to agree with the critics on
    the most important point they are making: controller-type logic, such as
    the code within page event handlers in ASP.NET, should not depend on the
    view elements.</para>

    <para>Having said that, there <emphasis>are</emphasis> good things about
    ASP.NET. Server-side forms and controls make developers significantly more
    productive and allow us to significantly simplify page markup. They also
    make cross-browser issues easier to deal with, as each control can make
    sure that it renders correct markup based on the user's browser. The
    ability to hook custom logic into the lifecycle of the page, as well as to
    customize HTTP processing pipeline are also very powerful features.
    Finally, being able to interact with the strongly typed server-side
    controls instead of manipulating string-based HTTP request collections,
    such as Form and QueryString, is a much needed layer of abstraction in web
    development.</para>

    <para>For these reasons, we decided that instead of developing a new,
    "pure and true MVC" web framework as part of Spring.NET, we should take a
    more pragmatic approach and extend ASP.NET in such a way that most, if not
    all of its shortcomings are eliminated. It should be noted that with the
    introduction of a 'true MVC framework' being added to .NET, with extension
    points for IoC containers such as Spring, Spring will continue to play a
    role within a MVC based model once that functionality is available from
    Microsoft. It is worth noting that Spring Java has a very popular MVC
    framework and much of that experience and added value can be
    transliterated to help developers be more productive when using the
    upcoming ASP.NET MVC support.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Spring.Web also adds support for applying the dependency injection
    principle to one's ASP.NET <classname>Pages</classname> and
    <classname>Controls</classname> as well as http modules and custom
    provider modules. This means that application developers can easily inject
    service dependencies into web controllers by leveraging the power of the
    Spring.NET IoC container. See <link linkend="web-di">Dependency Injection
    for ASP.NET Pages</link> for more information.</para>

    <para>As we said earlier, event handlers in code-behind classes really
    should not have to deal with ASP.NET UI controls directly. Such event
    handlers should rather work with the presentation model of the page,
    represented either as a hierarchy of domain objects or an ADO.NET
    <classname>DataSet</classname>. It is for that reason that the Spring.NET
    team implemented bidirectional data binding framework to handle the
    mapping of values to and from the controls on a page to the underlying
    data model. The data binding framework also transparently takes care of
    data type conversion and formatting, enabling application developers to
    work with fully typed data (domain) objects in the event handlers of
    code-behind files. See <link linkend="web-databinding">Bidirectional Data
    Binding and Model Management</link> for more information.</para>

    <para>The flow of control through an application is another area of
    concern that is addressed by Spring.NET Web Framework. Typical ASP.NET
    applications will use <literal>Response.Redirect</literal> or
    <literal>Server.Transfer</literal> calls within
    <classname>Page</classname> logic to navigate to an appropriate page after
    an action is executed. This typically leads to hard-coded target URLs in
    the <classname>Page</classname>, which is never a good thing. Result
    mapping solves this problem by allowing application developers to specify
    aliases for action results that map to target URLs based on information in
    an external configuration file that can easily be edited. Under
    consideration for future releases of Spring.NET is a process management
    framework, which will take this approach to another level, allowing you to
    control complex page flows in a very simple way. See <link
    linkend="web-resultmapping">Result Mapping</link> for more
    information.</para>

    <para>Standard localization support is also limited in versions of ASP.NET
    prior to ASP.NET 2.0. Even though Visual Studio 2003 generates a local
    resource file for each ASP.NET <classname>Page</classname> and user
    control, those resources are never used by the ASP.NET infrastructure.
    This means that application developers have to deal directly with resource
    managers whenever they need access to localized resources, which in the
    opinion of the Spring.NET team should not be the case. Spring.NET's Web
    Framework (hereafter referred to as Spring.Web) adds comprehensive support
    for localization using both local resource files and global resources that
    are configured within and for a Spring.NET container. See <link
    linkend="web-localization">Localization and Message Sources</link> for
    more information.</para>

    <para>In addition to the aforementioned features that can be considered to
    be the <emphasis>'core'</emphasis> features of the Spring.Web framework,
    Spring.Web also ships with a number of other lesser features that might be
    useful to a large number of application developers. Some of these
    additional features include back-ports of ASP.NET 2.0 features that can be
    used with ASP.NET 1.1, such as Master Page support. See <link lang=""
    linkend="web-masterpages">Master Pages in ASP.NET 1.1</link> for more
    information.</para>

    <para>In order to implement some of the above mentioned features the
    Spring.NET team had to extend (as in the object-oriented sense) the
    standard ASP.NET <classname>Page</classname> and
    <classname>UserControl</classname> classes. This means that in order to
    take advantage of the <emphasis>full</emphasis> feature stack of
    Spring.Web (most notably bidirectional data binding, localization and
    result mapping), your code-behind classes will have to extend Spring.Web
    specific base classes such as <classname>Spring.Web.UI.Page</classname>;
    however, some very powerful features such as dependency injection for
    ASP.NET Pages, Controls, and providers can be leveraged without having to
    extend Spring.Web-specific base classes. It is worth stating that by
    taking advantage of <emphasis>some</emphasis> of the more useful features
    offered by Spring.Web you will be coupling the presentation tier of your
    application(s) to Spring.Web. The choice of whether or not this is
    appropriate is, of course, left to you.</para>

    <para>Finally, please be aware that the standard Spring.NET distribution
    (as of v1.1) ships with a number of Web QuickStarts and a complete
    reference application, SpringAir. Web QuickStarts are the best way to
    learn each Spring.Web feature by following simple examples, and the
    SpringAir reference application has a Spring.Web-enabled frontend which
    uses many best practices for Spring.NET web applications, so please do
    refer to it as you are reading this (reference) material (see <xref
    linkend="springair" />).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-contexts">
    <title>Automatic context loading and hierarchical contexts</title>

    <sect2 id="web-configuration">
      <title>Configuration</title>

      <para>Unsurprisingly, Spring.Web builds on top of the Spring.NET IoC
      container, and makes heavy use (internally) of the easy pluggability and
      standardized configuration afforded by the IoC container. This also
      means that all of the controllers (ASP.NET <classname>Page</classname>s)
      that make up a typical Spring.Web enabled application will be configured
      using the same standard Spring.NET XML configuration syntax. Spring.Web
      uses a custom <classname>PageHandlerFactory</classname> implementation
      to load and configure a Spring.NET IoC container, which is in turn used
      to locate an appropriate <classname>Page</classname> to handle a HTTP
      request. The <classname>WebSupportModule</classname> configures
      miscellaneous Spring infrastructure classes for use in a web
      environment, for example setting the storage strategy of
      <classname>LogicalThreadContext</classname> to be
      <classname>HybridContextStorage</classname>.</para>

      <para>The instantiation and configuration of the Spring.NET IoC
      container by the Spring.Web infrastructure is wholly transparent to
      application developers, who will typically never have to explicitly
      instantiate and configure an IoC container manually (by for example
      using the <literal>new</literal> operator in C#). In order to effect the
      transparent bootstrapping of the IoC container, the Spring.Web
      infrastructure requires the insertion of the following configuration
      snippet into each and every Spring.Web-enabled web application's root
      <literal>Web.config</literal> file (the <literal>verb</literal> and
      <literal>path</literal> properties can of course be changed from the
      values that are shown below):</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;system.web&gt;
    &lt;httpHandlers&gt;
        &lt;add verb="*" path="*.aspx" type="Spring.Web.Support.PageHandlerFactory, Spring.Web"/&gt;
    &lt;/httpHandlers&gt;
    &lt;httpModules&gt;
        &lt;add name="Spring" type="Spring.Context.Support.WebSupportModule, Spring.Web"/&gt;
    &lt;/httpModules&gt;
    ...
&lt;/system.web&gt;

</programlisting>

      <para>Please note that this snippet of standard ASP.NET configuration is
      only required to be present in the <emphasis>root</emphasis> directory
      of each Spring.Web web application (i.e. in the
      <literal>web.config</literal> file present in the top level virtual
      directory of an ASP.NET web application).</para>

      <para>The above XML configuration snippet will direct the ASP.NET
      infrastructure to use Spring.NET's page factory, which will in turn
      create instances of the appropriate <literal>.aspx</literal>
      <classname>Page</classname>, (possibly) inject dependencies into said
      <classname>Page</classname> (as required), and then forward the handling
      of the request to said <classname>Page</classname>.</para>

      <para>After the Spring.Web page factory is configured, you will also
      need to define a root application context by adding a Spring.NET
      configuration section to that same <literal>web.config</literal> file.
      The final configuration file should look a little like this (your exact
      configuration will no doubt vary in particulars)...</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;

    &lt;configSections&gt;
        &lt;sectionGroup name="spring"&gt;
          &lt;section name="context" type="Spring.Context.Support.WebContextHandler, Spring.Web"/&gt;
        &lt;/sectionGroup&gt;
    &lt;/configSections&gt;

    &lt;spring&gt;
        &lt;context&gt;
            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/CommonObjects.xml"/&gt;
            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/CommonPages.xml"/&gt;

            &lt;!-- TEST CONFIGURATION --&gt;
            &lt;!--
            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/Test/Services.xml"/&gt;
            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/Test/Dao.xml"/&gt;
            --&gt;

            &lt;!-- PRODUCTION CONFIGURATION --&gt;

            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/Production/Services.xml"/&gt;
            &lt;resource uri="~/Config/Production/Dao.xml"/&gt;

        &lt;/context&gt;
    &lt;/spring&gt;

    &lt;system.web&gt;
        &lt;httpHandlers&gt;
            &lt;add verb="*" path="*.aspx" type="Spring.Web.Support.PageHandlerFactory, Spring.Web"/&gt;
        &lt;/httpHandlers&gt;
        &lt;httpModules&gt;
            &lt;add name="Spring" type="Spring.Context.Support.WebSupportModule, Spring.Web"/&gt;
        &lt;/httpModules&gt;
    &lt;/system.web&gt;

&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para>There are a few important points that need to be noted with regard
      to the above configuration:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You must define a custom configuration section handler for the
          <literal>spring/context</literal> element. If you use Spring.NET for
          many applications on the same web server, it might be easier to move
          the whole definition of the Spring.NET section group to your
          <literal>machine.config</literal> file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The custom configuration section handler is of the type
          <classname>Spring.Context.Support.WebContextHandler</classname>
          which will in turn instantiate an IoC container of the type
          <classname>Spring.Context.Support.WebApplicationContext</classname>.
          This will ensure that all of the features provided by Spring.Web are
          handled properly (such as request and session-scoped object
          definitions).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Within the &lt;spring&gt; element you need to define a root
          context, and resource locations that contain the object definitions
          that will be used within the web application (such as service or
          business tier objects) then need to be specified as child elements
          within the &lt;context&gt; element. Object definition resources can
          be fully-qualified paths or URLs, or non-qualified, as in the
          example above. Non-qualified resources will be loaded using the
          default resource type for the context, which for the
          <classname>WebApplicationContext</classname> is the
          <classname>WebResource</classname> type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Please note that the object definition resources do not all
          have to be the same resource type (e.g. all
          <literal>file://</literal>, all <literal>http://</literal>, all
          <literal>assembly://</literal>, etc). This means that you can load
          some object definitions from resources embedded directly within
          application assemblies (<literal>assembly://</literal>), while
          continuing to load other object definitions from web resources that
          can be more easily edited.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <sect3>
        <title>Configuration for IIS7</title>

        <para>The configuration for IIS7 is shown below</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;system.webServer&gt;
  &lt;validation validateIntegratedModeConfiguration="false"/&gt;
  &lt;modules&gt;
    &lt;add name="Spring" type="Spring.Context.Support.WebSupportModule, Spring.Web"/&gt;
  &lt;/modules&gt;
  &lt;handlers&gt;
    &lt;add name="SpringPageHandler" verb="*" path="*.aspx" type="Spring.Web.Support.PageHandlerFactory, Spring.Web"/&gt;
    &lt;add name="SpringContextMonitor" verb="*" path="ContextMonitor.ashx" type="Spring.Web.Support.ContextMonitor, Spring.Web"/&gt;
  &lt;/handlers&gt;
&lt;/system.webServer&gt;</programlisting>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-context-hierarchy">
      <title>Context Hierarchy</title>

      <para>ASP.NET provides a hierarchical configuration mechanism by
      allowing application developers to override configuration settings
      specified at a higher level in the web application directory hierarchy
      with configuration settings specified at the lower level.</para>

      <para>For example, a web application's root
      <literal>Web.config</literal> file overrides settings from the (lower
      level) <literal>machine.config</literal> file. In the same fashion,
      settings specified within the <literal>web.config</literal> file within
      a subdirectory of a web application will override settings from the root
      <literal>Web.config</literal> and so on. Lower level
      <literal>Web.config</literal> files can also add settings of their own
      that were not previously defined anywhere.</para>

      <para>Spring.Web leverages this ASP.NET feature to provide support for a
      context hierarchy. Your lower level <literal>Web.config</literal> files
      can be used to add new object definitions or to override existing ones
      per virtual directory.</para>

      <para>What this means to application developers is that one can easily
      componentize an application by creating a virtual directory per
      component and creating a custom context for each component that contains
      the necessary configuration info for that particular context. The
      configuration for a lower level component will generally contain only
      those definitions for the pages that the component consists of and
      (possibly) overrides for some of the definitions from the root context
      (for example, menus).</para>

      <para>Because each such lower level component will usually contain only
      a few object definitions, application developers are encouraged to embed
      those object definitions directly into the <literal>Web.config</literal>
      for the lower level context instead of relying on an external resource
      containing object definitions. This is easily accomplished by creating a
      component <literal>Web.config</literal> similar to the following
      one:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;

  &lt;configSections&gt;
    &lt;sectionGroup name="spring"&gt;
       &lt;section name="objects" type="Spring.Context.Support.DefaultSectionHandler, Spring.Core"/&gt;
    &lt;/sectionGroup&gt;
  &lt;/configSections&gt;

  &lt;spring&gt;
    &lt;context type="Spring.Context.Support.WebApplicationContext, Spring.Web"&gt;
        &lt;resource uri="config://spring/objects"/&gt;
    &lt;/context&gt;

    &lt;objects xmlns="http://www.springframework.net"&gt;
        &lt;object type="MyPage.aspx" parent="basePage"&gt;
              &lt;property name="MyRootService" ref="myServiceDefinedInRootContext"/&gt;
              &lt;property name="MyLocalService" ref="myServiceDefinedLocally"/&gt;
              &lt;property name="Results"&gt;
                 &lt;!-- ... --&gt;
              &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;/object&gt;
        &lt;object id="myServiceDefinedLocally" type="MyCompany.MyProject.Services.MyServiceImpl, MyAssembly"/&gt;
    &lt;/objects&gt;
  &lt;/spring&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The <literal>&lt;context/&gt;</literal> element seen above
      (contained within the <literal>&lt;spring/&gt;</literal> element) simply
      tells the Spring.NET infrastructure code to load (its) object
      definitions from the <literal>spring/objects</literal> section of the
      configuration file.</para>

      <para>You can (and should) avoid the need to specify
      <literal>&lt;configSections/&gt;</literal> element by moving the
      configuration handler definition for the
      <literal>&lt;objects&gt;</literal> element to a higher level (root)
      <literal>Web.config</literal> file, or even to the level of the
      <literal>machine.config</literal> file if Spring.NET is to be used for
      multiple applications on the same server.</para>

      <para>A very important point to be aware of is that this component-level
      context can reference definitions from its parent context(s). Basically,
      if a referenced object definition is not found in the current context,
      Spring.NET will search all the ancestor contexts in the context
      hierarchy until it finds said object definition (or ultimately fails and
      throws an exception).</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-di">
    <title>Dependency Injection for ASP.NET Pages</title>

    <para>Spring.Web builds on top of the feature set and capabilities of
    ASP.NET; one example of this can be seen the way that Spring.Web has used
    the code-behind class of the <classname>Page</classname> mechanism to
    satisfy the <literal>Controller</literal> portion of the MVC architectural
    pattern. In MVC-based (web) applications, the
    <literal>Controller</literal> is typically a thin wrapper around one or
    more service objects. In the specific case of Spring.Web, the Spring.NET
    team realized that it was very important that service object dependencies
    be easily injected into <classname>Page</classname>
    <literal>Controller</literal>s. Accordingly, Spring.Web provides first
    class support for dependency injection in ASP.NET
    <classname>Page</classname>s. This allows application developers to inject
    any required service object dependencies (and indeed any other
    dependencies) into their <classname>Page</classname>s using standard
    Spring.NET configuration instead of having to rely on custom service
    locators or manual object lookups in a Spring.NET application
    context.</para>

    <para>Once an application developer has <link
    linkend="web-configuration">configured</link> the Spring.NET web
    application context, said developer can easily create object definitions
    for the pages that compose that web application:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;objects xmlns="http://www.springframework.net"&gt;

  &lt;object name="basePage" abstract="true"&gt;
    &lt;property name="MasterPageFile" value="~/Web/StandardTemplate.master"/&gt;
  &lt;/object&gt;

  &lt;object type="Login.aspx"&gt;
      &lt;property name="Authenticator" ref="authenticationService"/&gt;
  &lt;/object&gt;

  &lt;object type="Default.aspx" parent="basePage"/&gt;

&lt;/objects&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>This example contains three definitions:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The first definition is an abstract definition for the base page
        that many other pages in the application will inherit from. In this
        case, the definition simply specifies which page is to be referenced
        as the master page, but it will typically also configure
        localization-related dependencies and root folders for images, scripts
        and CSS stylesheets.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The second definition defines a login page that neither inherits
        from the base page nor references the master page. What it does show
        is how to inject a service object dependency into a page instance (the
        <literal>authenticationService</literal> is defined elsewhere).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The final definition defines a default application page. In this
        case it simply inherits from the base page in order to inherit the
        master page dependency, but apart from that it doesn't need any
        additional dependency injection configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>One thing that slightly differentiates the configuration of ASP.NET
    pages from the configuration of other .NET classes is in the value passed
    to the <literal>type</literal> attribute. As can be seen in the above
    configuration snippet the <literal>type</literal> name is actually the
    path to the <literal>.aspx</literal> file for the
    <classname>Page</classname>, relative to the directory context it is
    defined in. In the case of the above example, those definitions are in the
    root context so <literal>Login.aspx</literal> and
    <literal>Default.aspx</literal> also must be in the root of the web
    application's virtual directory. The master page is defined using an
    absolute path because it could conceivably be referenced from child
    contexts that are defined within subdirectories of the web
    application.</para>

    <para>The astute reader may have noticed that the definitions for the
    <literal>Login</literal> and <literal>Default</literal> pages don't
    specify either of the <literal>id</literal> and <literal>name</literal>
    attributes. This is in marked contrast to typical object definitions in
    Spring.NET, where the <literal>id</literal> or <literal>name</literal>
    attributes are typically mandatory (although not always, as in the case of
    inner object definitions). This is actually intentional, because in the
    case of Spring.Web <classname>Page</classname>
    <literal>Controller</literal> instances one typically wants to use the
    name of the <literal>.aspx</literal> file name as the identifier. If an
    <literal>id</literal> is not specified, the Spring.Web infrastructure will
    simply use the name of the <literal>.aspx</literal> file as the object
    identifier (minus any leading path information, and minus the file
    extension too). </para>

    <para>Nothing prevents an application developer from specifying an
    <literal>id</literal> or <literal>name</literal> value explicitly; one use
    case when the explicit naming might be useful is when one wants to expose
    the same page multiple times using a slightly different configuration (Add
    / Edit pages for example). If you would like to use abstract object
    definitions and have your page inherit from them, the use of the name
    attribute should be used instead of the id attribute on the abstract
    object definition.</para>

    <sect2 id="web-di-controls">
      <title>Injecting Dependencies into Controls</title>

      <para>Spring.Web also allows application developers to inject
      dependencies into controls (both user controls and standard controls)
      that are contained within a page. This can be accomplished globally for
      all controls of a particular <literal>Type</literal> by using the
      location of the <literal>.ascx</literal> as the object type identifier.
      This is similar to injecting into <literal>.aspx </literal>pages shown
      above.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object type="~/controls/MyControl.ascx" abstract="true"&gt;
   &lt;!-- inject dependencies here... --&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>In either case, be sure to mark the object definition as
      <literal>abstract</literal> (by adding
      <literal>abstract="true"</literal> to the attribute list of the
      <literal>&lt;object/&gt;</literal> element).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Injecting dependencies into custom HTTP modules</title>

      <para>You can perform dependency injection on custom HTTP modules
      through the use of the class
      <classname>Spring.Context.Support.HttpApplicationConfigurer</classname>.
      You register your custom HTTP module as you would normally, for example
      a module of the type <classname>HtmlCommentAppenderModule</classname>,
      taken from the Web Quickstart, appends additional comments into the http
      response. It is registered as shown below</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;httpModules&gt;
  &lt;add name="HtmlCommentAppender" type="HtmlCommentAppenderModule"/&gt;
&lt;/httpModules&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>To configure this module, naming conventions are used to identify
      the module name with configuration instructions in the Spring
      configuration file. The ModuleTemplates property of
      HttpApplicationConfigurer is a dictionary that takes as a key the name
      of the HTTP module, HtmlCommentAppender, and as a value the
      configuration instructions as you would normally use for configuring an
      object with Spring. An example is shown below.
      HttpApplicationConfigurer' ModuleTemplates property.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object name="HttpApplicationConfigurer" type="Spring.Context.Support.HttpApplicationConfigurer, Spring.Web"&gt;
  &lt;property name="ModuleTemplates"&gt;
     &lt;dictionary&gt;
       &lt;entry key="HtmlCommentAppender"&gt; &lt;!-- this name must match the module name --&gt;
         &lt;object&gt;
           &lt;!-- select "view source" in your browser on any page to see the appended html comment --&gt;
           &lt;property name="AppendText" value="My configured comment!" /&gt;
         &lt;/object&gt;
       &lt;/entry&gt;
     &lt;/dictionary&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>You can see this example in action in the Web Quickstart.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Injecting dependencies into custom providers</title>

      <para>Custom providers can be configured with Spring. The approach to
      configuration is a family of adapters that correspond 1-to-1 with the
      standard ASP.NET providers that are registered using the standard
      ASP.NET mechanism. The adapters inherit from their correspondingly named
      provider class in the BCL.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>MembershipProviderAdapter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ProfileProviderAdapter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>RoleProviderAdapter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SiteMapProviderAdapter</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Here is an example of how to register the adapter for membership
      providers.</para>

      <programlisting>        &lt;membership defaultProvider="mySqlMembershipProvider"&gt;
            &lt;providers&gt;
                &lt;clear/&gt;
                &lt;add connectionStringName="" name="mySqlMembershipProvider" type="Spring.Web.Providers.MembershipProviderAdapter, Spring.Web"/&gt;
            &lt;/providers&gt;
        &lt;/membership&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The name of the provider must match the name of the object in the
      spring configuration that will serve as the actual provider
      implementation. For convenience there are configurable versions of the
      providers found in ASP.NET so that you can use the full functionality of
      spring to configure these standard provider implementations, for example
      using property place holders, etc. These are</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigurableActiveDirectoryMembershipProvider</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigurableSqlMembershipProvider</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigurableSqlProfileProvider</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigurableSqlRoleProvider</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigurableXmlSiteMapProvider</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Here is an example configuration taken from the Web Quickstart
      that simply sets the description property and connection string.</para>

      <programlisting>    &lt;object id="mySqlMembershipProvider" type="Spring.Web.Providers.ConfigurableSqlMembershipProvider"&gt;
        &lt;property name="connectionStringName" value="MyLocalSQLServer" /&gt;
        &lt;property name="parameters"&gt;
            &lt;name-values&gt;
                &lt;add key="description" value="membershipprovider description" /&gt;
            &lt;/name-values&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Your own custom providers of course will contain additional
      configuration specific to your implementation.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-controlling-di">
      <title>Customizing control dependency injection</title>

      <para>There might be situations where it is necessary to customize
      Spring.Web's dependency injection processing. In particular when using
      GridViews, which create a large number of child controls, dependency
      injection can slow down your page. To overcome this problem, you may
      tell Spring to handle the dependency injection process yourself by
      implementing the interface ISupportsWebDependencyInjection as shown
      below:</para>

      <programlisting>[C#]
class MyControl : Control, ISupportsWebDependencyInjection
{
  private IApplicationContext _defaultApplicationContext;

  public IApplicationContext DefaultApplicationContext
  {
    get { return _defaultApplicationContext; }
    set { _defaultApplicationContext = value; }
  }

  override protected AddedControl( Control control, int index )
  {
    // handle DI for children ourselves -
    // defaults to a call to InjectDependenciesRecursive
    WebUtils.InjectDependenciesRecursive( _defaultApplicationContext, control );
    base.AddedControl( control, index );
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>There is a Spring server control, Panel, that provides an easier
      way to turn of dependency injection for parts of your page. Example use
      is shown below</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;spring:Panel runat="server"
   suppressDependencyInjection="true"  
   renderContainerTag="false"&gt;

   .. put your heavy controls here - they won't be touched by DI

&lt;/spring:Panel&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>By wrapping the performance sensitive parts of your page within
      this panel, you can easily turn off DI using the attribute
      suppressDependencyInjection. By default &lt;spring:Panel/&gt; won't
      render a container tag (&lt;div&gt;, &lt;span&gt;, etc.). You can modify
      this behavior by setting the attribute "renderContainerTag"
      accordingly.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-objectscope">
    <title>Object Scope</title>

    <para>Spring.NET web applications support an additional attribute within
    object definition elements that allows you to control the scope of an
    object: <programlisting>&lt;object id="myObject" type="MyType, MyAssembly" scope="application | session | request"/&gt;</programlisting>As
    you can see, there are three possible values for the scope attribute --
    application, session or request. Application scope is the default, and
    will be used for all objects that don't have scope attribute defined. As
    its name says, it will result in a single instance of an object being
    created for the duration of the application, so it works exactly like the
    standard singleton objects in non-web applications. Session scope allows
    you to define objects in such a way that an instance is created for each
    HttpSession. This is the ideal scope for objects that you want bound to a
    single user such as user profile, shopping cart, etc. Request scope will
    result in a creation of an instance per HTTP request.</para>

    <para>Unlike with prototype objects, calls to
    <literal>IApplicationContext.GetObject</literal> will return the same
    instance of the request-scoped object during a single HTTP request. This
    allows you, for example, to inject the same request-scoped object into
    multiple pages and then use server-side transfer to move from one page to
    another. As all the pages are executed within the single HTTP request in
    this case, they will share the same instance of the injected
    object.</para>

    <para>One thing to keep in mind is that objects can only reference other
    objects that are in the same or broader scope. This means that
    application-scoped objects can only reference other application-scoped,
    session-scoped objects can reference both session and application-scoped
    objects, and finally, request-scoped objects can reference other request,
    session or application-scoped objects. Also, prototype objects (and that
    includes all ASP.NET web pages defined within Spring.NET context) can
    reference singleton objects from any scope, as well as other prototype
    objects.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-masterpages">
    <title>Master Pages in ASP.NET 1.1</title>

    <para>Support for ASP.NET 1.1 master pages in Spring.Web is very similar
    to the support for master pages in ASP.NET 2.0.</para>

    <para>The idea is that a web developer can define a layout template for
    the site as a master page and specify content place holders that other
    pages can then reference and populate. A sample master page
    (<literal>MasterLayout.ascx</literal>) could look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;%@ Control language="c#" Codebehind="MasterLayout.ascx.cs" AutoEventWireup="false" Inherits="MyApp.Web.UI.MasterLyout" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0 Transitional//EN" &gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Master Page&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="&lt;%= Context.Request.ApplicationPath %&gt;/css/styles.css"&gt;
        &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="head" runat="server"/&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;form runat="server"&gt;
            &lt;table cellPadding="3" width="100%" border="1"&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td colspan="2"&gt;
                        &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="title" runat="server"&gt;
                            &lt;!-- default title content --&gt;
                        &lt;/spring:ContentPlaceHolder&gt;
                    &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;
                        &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="leftSidebar" runat="server"&gt;
                            &lt;!-- default left side content --&gt;
                        &lt;/spring:ContentPlaceHolder&gt;
                    &lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;
                        &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="main" runat="server"&gt;
                            &lt;!-- default main area content --&gt;
                        &lt;/spring:ContentPlaceHolder&gt;
                    &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/table&gt;
        &lt;/form&gt;
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>As you can see from the above code, the master page defines the
    overall layout for the page, in addition to four content placeholders that
    other pages can override. The master page can also include default content
    within the placeholder that will be displayed if a derived page does not
    override the placeholder.</para>

    <para>A page (Child.aspx) that uses this master page might look like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Page language="c#" Codebehind="Child.aspx.cs" AutoEventWireup="false" Inherits="ArtFair.Web.UI.Forms.Child" %&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;

        &lt;spring:Content id="leftSidebarContent" contentPlaceholderId="leftSidebar" runat="server"&gt;
            &lt;!-- left sidebar content --&gt;
        &lt;/spring:Content&gt;

        &lt;spring:Content id="mainContent" contentPlaceholderId="main" runat="server"&gt;
            &lt;!-- main area content --&gt;
        &lt;/spring:Content&gt;

    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>&lt;spring:Content/&gt;</literal> control in the above
    example uses the <literal>contentPlaceholderId</literal> attribute
    (property) to specify exactly which placeholder from the master page is to
    be overridden. Because this particular page does not define content
    elements for the head and title place holders, they will be displayed
    using the default content supplied in the master page.</para>

    <para>Both the <classname>ContentPlaceHolder</classname> and
    <classname>Content</classname> controls can contain any valid ASP.NET
    markup: HTML, standard ASP.NET controls, user controls, etc.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>VS.NET 2003 issue</title>

      <para>Technically, the <literal>&lt;html&gt;</literal> and
      <literal>&lt;body&gt;</literal> tags from the previous example are not
      strictly necessary because they are already defined in the master page.
      However, if these tags are omitted, then Visual Studio 2003 will
      complain about a schema and intellisense won't work, so it's much easier
      to work in the HTML view if those tags are included. They will be
      ignored when the page is rendered.</para>
    </tip>

    <sect2 id="web-childpage-linking">
      <title>Linking child pages to their master</title>

      <para>The <classname>Spring.Web.UI.Page</classname> class exposes a
      property called <literal>MasterPageFile</literal>, which can be used to
      specify the master page.</para>

      <para>The recommended way to do this is by leveraging the Spring.NET IoC
      container and creating definitions similar to the following:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?&gt;
&lt;objects xmlns="http://www.springframework.net"&gt;

  &lt;object name="basePage" abstract="true"&gt;
      &lt;property name="MasterPageFile" value="~/MasterLayout.ascx"/&gt;
  &lt;/object&gt;

  &lt;object type="Child.aspx" parent="basePage"&gt;
      &lt;!-- inject other objects that page needs --&gt;
  &lt;/object&gt;

&lt;/objects&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>This approach allows application developers to change the master
      page being used for a number of pages within a web application. Of
      course, the master page can still be overridden on a per context or per
      page basis by creating a new abstract page definition within a child
      context, or by specifying the <literal>MasterPageFile</literal> property
      directly.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-databinding">
    <title>Bidirectional Data Binding and Model Management</title>

    <para>A problem with the existing data binding support in ASP.NET is that
    it is one-way only. It allows application developers to bind page controls
    to the data model and display information from said data model, but it
    doesn't allow for the extraction of values from the controls when the form
    is submitted. Spring.Web adds such bidirectional data binding to ASP.NET
    by allowing developers to specify data binding rules for their page, and
    by automatically evaluating configured data binding rules at the
    appropriate time in the page's lifecycle.</para>

    <para>ASP.NET also doesn't provide any support for model management within
    the postbacks. Sure, it has a ViewState management, but that takes care of
    the control state only and not of the state of any presentation model
    objects these controls might be bound to. In order to manage model within
    ASP.NET, developers will typically use HTTP Session object to store the
    model between the postbacks. This results in a decent amount of
    boilerplate code that can and should be eliminated, which is exactly what
    Spring.Web does by providing a simple set of model management
    methods.</para>

    <para>Please note that in order to take advantage of the bidirectional
    data binding and model management support provided by Spring.Web, you
    <emphasis>will</emphasis> have to couple your presentation layer to
    Spring.Web; this is because features <emphasis>requires</emphasis> you to
    extend a <classname>Spring.Web.UI.Page</classname> instead of the usual
    <classname>System.Web.UI.Page</classname> class.</para>

    <para>Spring.Web data binding is very easy to use. Application developers
    simply need to override the protected
    <literal>InitializeDataBindings</literal> method and configure data
    binding rules for the page. They also need to override three model
    management methods: <literal>InitializeModel</literal>,
    <literal>LoadModel</literal> and <literal>SaveModel</literal>. This is
    perhaps best illustrated by an example from the SpringAir reference
    application. First, let's take a look at the page markup:<programlisting>&lt;%@ Page Language="c#" Inherits="TripForm" CodeFile="TripForm.aspx.cs" %&gt;

&lt;asp:Content ID="body" ContentPlaceHolderID="body" runat="server"&gt;
    &lt;div style="text-align: center"&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;&lt;asp:Label ID="caption" runat="server"&gt;&lt;/asp:Label&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;table&gt;
            &lt;tr class="formLabel"&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td colspan="3"&gt;
                    &lt;spring:RadioButtonGroup ID="tripMode" runat="server"&gt;
                        &lt;asp:RadioButton ID="OneWay" runat="server" /&gt;
                        &lt;asp:RadioButton ID="RoundTrip" runat="server" /&gt;
                    &lt;/spring:RadioButtonGroup&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td class="formLabel" align="right"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:Label ID="leavingFrom" runat="server" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td nowrap="nowrap"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:DropDownList ID="leavingFromAirportCode" runat="server" /&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td class="formLabel" align="right"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:Label ID="goingTo" runat="server" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td nowrap="nowrap"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:DropDownList ID="goingToAirportCode" runat="server" /&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td class="formLabel" align="right"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:Label ID="leavingOn" runat="server" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td nowrap="nowrap"&gt;
                    &lt;spring:Calendar ID="departureDate" runat="server" Width="75px" AllowEditing="true" Skin="system" /&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td class="formLabel" align="right"&gt;
                    &lt;asp:Label ID="returningOn" runat="server" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td nowrap="nowrap"&gt;
                    &lt;div id="returningOnCalendar"&gt;
                        &lt;spring:Calendar ID="returnDate" runat="server" Width="75px" AllowEditing="true" Skin="system" /&gt;
                    &lt;/div&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td class="buttonBar" colspan="4"&gt;
                    &lt;br/&gt;
                    &lt;asp:Button ID="findFlights" runat="server"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

 &lt;/asp:Content&gt;

</programlisting>Ignore for the moment the fact that none of the label
    controls have text defined, which will be described later when we discuss
    localization in Spring.NET. What is important for the purposes of our
    current discussion, is that we have a number of input controls defined:
    <literal>tripMode</literal> radio group,
    <literal>leavingFromAirportCode</literal> and
    <literal>goingToAirportCode</literal> dropdowns, as well as two Spring.NET
    Calendar controls, <literal>departureDate</literal> and
    <literal>returnDate</literal>.</para>

    <para>Next, let's take a look at the model we will be binding this form
    to:<programlisting>namespace SpringAir.Domain
{
    [Serializable]
    public class Trip
    {
        // fields
        private TripMode mode;
        private TripPoint startingFrom;
        private TripPoint returningFrom;

        // constructors
        public Trip()
        {
            this.mode = TripMode.RoundTrip;
            this.startingFrom = new TripPoint();
            this.returningFrom = new TripPoint();
        }

        public Trip(TripMode mode, TripPoint startingFrom, TripPoint returningFrom)
        {
            this.mode = mode;
            this.startingFrom = startingFrom;
            this.returningFrom = returningFrom;
        }

        // properties
        public TripMode Mode
        {
            get { return this.mode; }
            set { this.mode = value; }
        }

        public TripPoint StartingFrom
        {
            get { return this.startingFrom; }
            set { this.startingFrom = value; }
        }

        public TripPoint ReturningFrom
        {
            get { return this.returningFrom; }
            set { this.returningFrom = value; }
        }
    }

    [Serializable]
    public class TripPoint
    {
        // fields
        private string airportCode;
        private DateTime date;

        // constructors
        public TripPoint()
        {}

        public TripPoint(string airportCode, DateTime date)
        {
            this.airportCode = airportCode;
            this.date = date;
        }

        // properties
        public string AirportCode
        {
            get { return this.airportCode; }
            set { this.airportCode = value; }
        }

        public DateTime Date
        {
            get { return this.date; }
            set { this.date = value; }
        }
    }

    [Serializable]
    public enum TripMode
    {
        OneWay,
        RoundTrip
    }
}</programlisting>As you can see, <classname>Trip</classname> class uses the
    <classname>TripPoint</classname> class to represent departure and return,
    which are exposed as <literal>StartingFrom</literal> and
    <literal>ReturningFrom</literal> properties. It also uses
    <classname>TripMode</classname> enumeration to specify whether the trip is
    one way or return trip, which is exposed as <literal>Mode</literal>
    property.</para>

    <para>Finally, let's see the code-behind class that ties everything
    together:<programlisting>public class TripForm : Spring.Web.UI.Page
{
    // model
    private Trip trip;
    public Trip Trip
    {
        get { return trip; }
        set { trip = value; }
    }

    // service dependency, injected by Spring IoC container
    private IBookingAgent bookingAgent;
    public IBookingAgent BookingAgent
    {
        set { bookingAgent = value; }
    }

    // model management methods
    protected override void InitializeModel()
    {
        trip = new Trip();
        trip.Mode = TripMode.RoundTrip;
        trip.StartingFrom.Date = DateTime.Today;
        trip.ReturningFrom.Date = DateTime.Today.AddDays(1);
    }

    protected override void LoadModel(object savedModel)
    {
        trip = (Trip) savedModel;
    }

    protected override object SaveModel()
    {
        return trip;
    }

    // data binding rules
    protected override void InitializeDataBindings()
    {
        BindingManager.AddBinding("tripMode.Value", "Trip.Mode");
        BindingManager.AddBinding("leavingFromAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.StartingFrom.AirportCode");
        BindingManager.AddBinding("goingToAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.ReturningFrom.AirportCode");
        BindingManager.AddBinding("departureDate.SelectedDate", "Trip.StartingFrom.Date");
        BindingManager.AddBinding("returnDate.SelectedDate", "Trip.ReturningFrom.Date");
    }

    // event handler for findFlights button, uses injected 'bookingAgent'
    // service and model 'trip' object to find flights
    private void SearchForFlights(object sender, EventArgs e)
    {
        FlightSuggestions suggestions = bookingAgent.SuggestFlights(trip);
        if (suggestions.HasOutboundFlights)
        {
            // redirect to SuggestedFlights page
        }
    }
}</programlisting>There are quite a few things that are happening in this
    relatively simple piece of code, so it's worth that we spend some time on
    each one:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>When the page is initially loaded (<literal>IsPostback ==
          false</literal>), the <literal>InitializeModel</literal> method is
          called which initializes the trip object by creating a new instance
          and setting its properties to desired values. Right before the page
          is rendered, <literal>the SaveModel</literal> method will be invoked
          and whatever the value it returns will be stored within the HTTP
          Session. Finally, on each postback, <literal>the LoadModel</literal>
          method will be called and the value returned by the previous call to
          <literal>SaveModel</literal> will be passed to it as an
          argument.</para>

          <para>In this particular case the implementation is very simple
          because our whole model is just the <literal>trip</literal> object.
          As such, <literal>SaveModel</literal> simply returns the
          <literal>trip</literal> object and <literal>LoadModel</literal>
          casts the <literal>savedModel</literal> argument to
          <classname>Trip</classname> and assigns it to the
          <literal>trip</literal> field within the page. In the more complex
          scenarios, you will typically return a dictionary containing your
          model objects from the <literal>SaveModel</literal> method, and read
          the values from that dictionary within the
          <literal>LoadModel</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>InitializeDataBindings</literal> method defines the
          binding rules for all five input controls on our form. It does so by
          invoking <literal>AddBinding</literal> method on the
          <literal>BindingManager</literal> exposed by the page.
          <literal>AddBinding</literal> method is heavily overloaded and it
          allows you to specify a <emphasis>binding direction</emphasis> and a
          <emphasis>formatter</emphasis> to use in addition to the
          <emphasis>source and target binding expressions</emphasis> that are
          used above. We'll discuss these optional parameters shortly, but for
          now let's focus on the source and target expressions.</para>

          <para>The Data Binding framework uses Spring.NET Expression Language
          to define binding expressions. In most cases, like in the example
          above, both source and target expression will evaluate to a property
          or a field within one of the controls or a data model. This is
          always the case when you are setting a bi-directional binding, as
          both binding expressions need to be "settable". What is important to
          remember about <literal>InitializeDataBindings</literal> method is
          that it is executed only once <emphasis>per page type</emphasis>.
          Basically, all of the binding expressions are parsed the first time
          the page is instantiated, and are the cached and used by all
          instances of that same page type that are created at a later time.
          This is done for performance reasons, as data binding expression
          parsing on every postback is unnecessary and would add a significant
          overhead to the overall page processing time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you look at the SearchForFlights event handler, you will
          notice that it has no dependencies on the view elements. It simply
          uses the injected bookingAgent service and a trip object that in
          order to obtain a list of suggested flights. Furthermore, if you
          make any modifications to the trip object within your event handler,
          bound controls will be updated accordingly just before the page is
          rendered.</para>

          <para>This accomplishes one of the major goals we set out to
          achieve, allowing developers to remove view element references from
          the page event handlers and decouple controller-type methods from
          the view.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>Now that you have a solid high-level picture of how Spring.NET data
    binding and model management are typically used in web applications, let's
    take a look at the details and see how data binding is actually
    implemented under the hood, what the extension points are, and what are
    some additional features that make data binding framework usable in
    real-world applications.</para>

    <sect2 id="web-binding-detail">
      <title>Data Binding Under the Hood</title>

      <para>Spring.NET Data Binding framework revolves around two main
      interfaces: <literal>IBinding</literal> and
      <literal>IBindingContainer</literal>. The <literal>IBinding</literal>
      interface is definitely the more important one of the two, as it has to
      be implemented by all binding types. This interface defines several
      methods, with some of them being overloaded for
      convenience:<programlisting>public interface IBinding
{
    void BindSourceToTarget(object source, object target, ValidationErrors validationErrors);

    void BindSourceToTarget(object source, object target, ValidationErrors validationErrors, 
                            IDictionary variables);

    void BindTargetToSource(object source, object target, ValidationErrors validationErrors);

    void BindTargetToSource(object source, object target, ValidationErrors validationErrors, 
                            IDictionary variables);

    void SetErrorMessage(string messageId, params string[] errorProviders);
}</programlisting>As their names imply, <literal>BindSourceToTarget</literal>
      method is used to extract and copy bound values from the source object
      to the target object, while <literal>BindTargetToSource</literal> does
      the opposite. Both method names and parameter types are very generic for
      a good reason -- data binding framework can indeed be used to bind any
      two objects. Using it to bind web forms to model objects is just one of
      its possible uses, although a very common one and tightly integrated
      into the Spring.NET Web Framework.</para>

      <para>The <literal>validationErrors</literal> parameter requires further
      explanation. While the data binding framework is not in any way coupled
      to the data validation framework, they are in some ways related. For
      example, while the data validation framework is best suited to validate
      the populated model according to the business rules, the data binding
      framework is in a better position to validate data types during the
      binding process. However, regardless of where specific validation is
      performed, all error messages should be presented to the user in a
      consistent manner. In order to accomplish this, Spring.NET Web Framework
      passes the same ValidationErrors instance to binding methods and to any
      validators that might be executed within your event handlers. This
      ensures that all error messages are stored together and are displayed
      consistently to the end user, using Spring.NET validation error
      controls.</para>

      <para>The last method in the <literal>IBinding</literal> interface,
      <literal>SetErrorMessage</literal>, enables this by allowing you to
      specify the resource id of the error message to be displayed in the case
      of binding error, as well as the list of error providers that messages
      should be displayed in. We will see an example of the
      <literal>SetErrorMessage</literal> usage shortly.</para>

      <para>The <literal>IBindingContainer</literal> interface extends the
      <literal>IBinding</literal> interface and adds the following
      members:<programlisting>public interface IBindingContainer : IBinding
{
  bool HasBindings { get; }

  IBinding AddBinding(IBinding binding);
  IBinding AddBinding(string sourceExpression, string targetExpression);
  IBinding AddBinding(string sourceExpression, string targetExpression, BindingDirection direction);
  IBinding AddBinding(string sourceExpression, string targetExpression, IFormatter formatter);
  IBinding AddBinding(string sourceExpression, string targetExpression, BindingDirection direction, 
                      IFormatter formatter);
}</programlisting>As you can see, this interface has a number of overloaded
      <literal>AddBinding</literal> methods. The first one,
      <literal>AddBinding(IBinding binding)</literal> is the most generic one,
      as it can be used to add any binding type to the container. The other
      four are convenience methods that provide a simple way to add the most
      commonly used binding type, <literal>SimpleExpressionBinding</literal>.
      The <literal>SimpleExpressionBinding</literal> is what we used in the
      example at the beginning of this section to bind our web form to a
      <classname>Trip</classname> instance. It uses Spring.NET Expression
      Language to extract and to set values within source and target objects.
      We discussed <literal>sourceExpression</literal> and
      <literal>targetExpression</literal> arguments earlier, so let's focus on
      the remaining ones.</para>

      <sect3 id="web-binding-direction">
        <title>Binding Direction</title>

        <para>The direction argument determines whether the binding is
        bidirectional or unidirectional. By default, all data bindings are
        bidirectional unless the direction argument is set to either
        <literal>BindingDirection.SourceToTarget</literal> or
        <literal>BindingDirection.TargetToSource</literal>. If one of these
        two values is specified, binding will be evaluated only when the
        appropriate <literal>Bind</literal><emphasis>Direction</emphasis>
        method is invoked, and will be completely ignored in the other
        direction. This is very useful when you want to bind some information
        from the model into non-input controls, such as labels.</para>

        <para>However, unidirectional data bindings are also useful when your
        form doesn't have a simple one-to-one mapping to presentation model.
        In our earlier trip form example, the presentation model was
        intentionally designed to allow for simple one-to-one mappings. For
        the sake of discussion, let's add the <classname>Airport</classname>
        class and modify our <classname>TripPoint</classname> class like
        this:<programlisting>namespace SpringAir.Domain
{
    [Serializable]
    public class TripPoint
    {
        // fields
        private Airport airport;
        private DateTime date;

        // constructors
        public TripPoint()
        {}

        public TripPoint(Airport airport, DateTime date)
        {
            this.airport = airport;
            this.date = date;
        }

        // properties
        public Airport Airport
        {
            get { return this.airport; }
            set { this.airport = value; }
        }

        public DateTime Date
        {
            get { return this.date; }
            set { this.date = value; }
        }
    }

    [Serializable]
    public class Airport
    {
        // fields
        private string code;
        private string name;

       // properties
        public string Code
        {
            get { return this.code; }
            set { this.code = value; }
        }

        public string Name
        {
            get { return this.name; }
            set { this.name = value; }
        }
    }
}</programlisting>Instead of the string property
        <literal>AirportCode</literal>, our <classname>TripPoint</classname>
        class now exposes an <literal>Airport</literal> property of type
        <classname>Airport</classname>, which is defined above. Now we have a
        problem: what used to be a simple string to string binding, with the
        airport code selected in a dropdown being copied directly into the
        TripPoint.AirportCode property and vice versa, now becomes a not so
        simple string to <classname>Airport</classname> binding, so let's see
        how we can solve this mismatch problem.</para>

        <para>First of all, binding from the model to the control is still
        very straight forward. We just need to set up one-way bindings from
        the model to controls:<programlisting>protected override void InitializeDataBindings()
    {
        BindingManager.AddBinding("leavingFromAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.StartingFrom.Airport.Code", BindingDirection.TargetToSource);
        BindingManager.AddBinding("goingToAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.ReturningFrom.Airport.Code", BindingDirection.TargetToSource);
        ...
    }</programlisting>All we need to do is extract airport code value from the
        <literal>Trip.StartingFrom.Airport.Code</literal> instead of
        <literal>Trip.StartingFrom.AirportCode</literal>. Unfortunately,
        binding from the control to the model the same way won't work: we
        might be able to set <literal>Code</literal> property of the
        <classname>Airport</classname> object, but that will likely make the
        <literal>Airport.Name</literal> property invalid. What we really want
        do is find an instance of the <classname>Airport</classname> class
        based on the airport code and set the
        <literal>TripPoint.Airport</literal> property to it. Fortunately, this
        is very simple to do with Spring.NET data binding, especially because
        we already have <literal>airportDao</literal> object defined in the
        Spring context, which has <literal>GetAirport(string
        airportCode)</literal> finder method. All we need to do is set up data
        bindings from source to target that will invoke this finder method
        when evaluating the source expression. Our complete set of bindings
        for these two drop down lists will then look like
        this:<programlisting>protected override void InitializeDataBindings()
    {
        BindingManager.AddBinding("@(airportDao).GetAirport(leavingFromAirportCode.SelectedValue)", "Trip.StartingFrom.Airport", BindingDirection.SourceToTarget);
        BindingManager.AddBinding("leavingFromAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.StartingFrom.Airport.Code", BindingDirection.TargetToSource);

        BindingManager.AddBinding("@(airportDao).GetAirport(goingToAirportCode.SelectedValue)", "Trip.ReturningFrom.Airport", BindingDirection.SourceToTarget);
        BindingManager.AddBinding("goingToAirportCode.SelectedValue", "Trip.ReturningFrom.Airport.Code", BindingDirection.TargetToSource);
        ...
    }</programlisting>That's it -- by using two unidirectional bindings with
        different expressions and by leveraging the fact that expressions can
        reference objects defined in the Spring context, we were able to solve
        this non-trivial data binding problem.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-binding-formatters">
        <title>Formatters</title>

        <para>The last argument to <literal>AddBinding</literal> method that
        we need to discuss is a <literal>formatter</literal> argument. This
        argument allows you to specify a formatter that should be used to
        parse string value from the typical input control before it is bound
        to the model, and to format strongly typed model value before it is
        bound to the control.</para>

        <para>You will typically use one of the formatters provided in the
        Spring.Globalization.Formatters namespace, but if you have
        requirements that cannot be satisfied by one of the standard
        formatters it is easy enough to write your own -- all you need to do
        is implement a very simple IFormatter interface:<programlisting>public interface IFormatter
{
    string Format(object value);
    object Parse(string value);
}</programlisting></para>

        <para>Standard formatters provided with Spring.NET are:
        <literal>CurrencyFormatter</literal>,
        <literal>DateTimeFormatter</literal>,
        <literal>FloatFormatter</literal>,
        <literal>IntegerFormatter</literal>,
        <literal>NumberFormatter</literal> and
        <literal>PercentFormatter</literal>, which should be sufficient for
        most usage scenarios.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-id-typeconversion">
        <title>Type Conversion</title>

        <para>Because the data binding framework uses the same expression
        evaluation engine as the Spring.NET IoC container, it will use any
        registered type converters to perform data binding. Many type
        converters are included with Spring.NET (take a look at the classes in
        Spring.Objects.TypeConverters namespace) and automatically registered
        for you, but you can implement your own custom converters and register
        them using standard Spring.NET type converter registration
        mechanisms.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-binding-events">
        <title>Data Binding Events</title>

        <para>Spring.Web's base <classname>Page</classname> class adds two
        events to the standard .NET page lifecycle -
        <literal>DataBound</literal> and
        <literal>DataUnbound</literal>.</para>

        <para>The <literal>DataUnbound</literal> event is fired after the data
        model has been updated using values from the controls. It is fired
        right after the <literal>Load</literal> event and only on postbacks,
        because it doesn't make sense to update the data model using the
        controls' initial values.</para>

        <para>The <literal>DataBound</literal> is fired after controls have
        been updated using values from the data model. This happens right
        before the <literal>PreRender</literal> event.</para>

        <para>The fact that data model is updated immediately after the
        <literal>Load</literal> event and that controls are updated right
        before the <literal>PreRender</literal> event means that your event
        handlers will be able to work with a correctly updated data model, as
        they execute after the <literal>Load</literal> event, and that any
        changes you make to the data model within event handlers will be
        reflected in the controls immediately afterwards, as they (the
        controls) are updated prior to the actual rendering.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-binding-errors">
        <title>Rendering Binding Errors</title>

        <para>If there are errors in the databinding, for example, trying to
        bind a string 'hello' to an integer property on the model, you can
        specify how those fundamental binding errors should be rendered. An
        example of this shown below taken from the WebQuickStart
        'RobustEmployeeInfo' example.</para>

        <programlisting>[Default.aspx.cs]

protected override void InitializeDataBindings()
{
  // collect txtId.Text binding errors in "id.errors" collection
  BindingManager.AddBinding("txtId.Text", "Employee.Id").SetErrorMessage("ID has to be an integer", "id.errors");
  ...

[Default.aspx]
...
&lt;asp:TextBox ID="txtId" runat="server" /&gt;
&lt;!-- output validation errors from "id.errors" collection --&gt;
&lt;spring:ValidationError Provider="id.errors" runat="server" /&gt;
...</programlisting>

        <para>The SetErrorMessage specifies the message text or resource id of
        the error message to be displayed followed by a variable length list
        of strings that specify the collection of error providers message
        where the message should be displayed. In the above case the error
        provider will be rendered in Spring's ValidationError User Control.
        See</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-binding-list">
        <title>HttpRequestListBindingContainer</title>

        <para>HttpRequestListBindingContainer extracts posted raw values from
        the request and populates the specified IList by creating objects of
        the type specified and populating each of these objects according to
        the requestBindings collection.</para>

        <para>Please checkout the WebQuickStart sample's demo of
        HttpRequestListBindingContainer. Below</para>

        <para><programlisting>protected override void InitializeDataBindings()
{
  // HttpRequestListBindingContainer unbinds specified values from Request -&gt; Productlist
  HttpRequestListBindingContainer requestBindings =
      new HttpRequestListBindingContainer("sku,name,quantity,price", "Products", typeof(ProductInfo));
  requestBindings.AddBinding("sku", "Sku");
  requestBindings.AddBinding("name", "Name");
  requestBindings.AddBinding("quantity", "Quantity", quantityFormatter);
  requestBindings.AddBinding("price", "Price", priceFormatter);

  BindingManager.AddBinding(requestBindings);
}</programlisting></para>

        <note>
           Due to the fact, that browsers don't send the values of unchecked checkboxes, you can't use HttpRequestListBindingContainer with &lt;input type="checkbox" &gt; html controls. 
        </note>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-databindingpanel">
      <title>Using DataBindingPanel</title>

      <para>To simplify use of Spring's Data Binding feature on web pages and
      controls, Spring.Web provides a special DataBindingPanel container
      control. A DataBindingPanel does not render any html code itself, but
      allows for specifying additional, data binding related attributes to its
      child controls:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;%@ Page Language="C#" CodeFile="Default.aspx.cs" Inherits="DataBinding_EasyEmployeeInfo_Default" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;spring:DataBindingPanel ID="ctlDataBindingPanel" runat="server"&gt;
    &lt;table cellpadding="3" cellspacing="3" border="0"&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Employee ID:&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;asp:TextBox ID="txtId" runat="server" BindingTarget="Employee.Id" /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;First Name:&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:TextBox ID="txtFirstName" runat="server" BindingTarget="Employee.FirstName" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/spring.DataBindingPanel&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para>Using DataBindingPanel the binding information can be specified
      directly on the control declaration. The following attributes are
      recognized by a DataBindingPanel:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>BindingTarget</para>

          <para>corresponds to the target expression used in
          IBindingContainer.AddBinding()</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>BindingSource</para>

          <para>corresponds to the source expression used in
          IBindingContainer.AddBinding(). For standard controls you don't need
          to specify the source expression. If you are binding to some custom
          control, of course you must specific this attribute.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>BindingDirection</para>

          <para>one of the values of the BindingDirection enumeration</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>BindingFormatter</para>

          <para>if you need a custom formatter, you can specific the object
          name of a formatter here. The formatter instance will be obtained by
          a call to IApplicationContext.GetObject() each time it is
          needed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>BindingType</para>

          <para>In case you need a completely customized binding, specify its
          type here. Note that a custom binding type must implement the
          following constructor signature:</para>

          <para><literal>ctor(string source,string target, BindingDirection,
          IFormatter)</literal></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
         The Visual Studio Web Form Editor will of course complain about binding attributes because it doesn't know them. You can safely ignore those warnings. 
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-localization">
    <title>Localization and Message Sources</title>

    <para>While recognizing that the .NET framework has excellent support for
    localization, the support within ASP.NET 1.x is somewhat
    incomplete.</para>

    <para>Every <literal>.aspx</literal> page in an ASP.NET project has a
    resource file associated with it, but those resources are never used (by
    the current ASP.NET infrastructure). ASP.NET 2.0 will change that and
    allow application developers to use local resources for pages. In the
    meantime, the Spring.NET team built support for using local pages
    resources into Spring.Web thus allowing application developers to start
    using ASP.NET 2.0-like page resources immediately.</para>

    <para>Spring.Web supports several different approaches to localization
    within a web application, which can be mixed and matched as appropriate.
    Both push and pull mechanisms are supported, as well as the fallback to
    globally defined resources when a local resource cannot be found.
    Spring.Web also provides support for user culture management and image
    localization, which are described in the later sections.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>Introductory material covering ASP.NET Globalization and
      Localization can be found at the following URLs; <ulink
      url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/asp.net/community/authors/mlb/default.aspx?pull=/library/en-us/dnaspp/html/aspnet-globalarchi.asp">Globalization
      Architecture for ASP.NET</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://www.theserverside.net/articles/showarticle.tss?id=LocalizationPractices">Localization
      Practices for ASP.NET 2.0</ulink> by Michele Leroux Bustamante.</para>
    </tip>

    <sect2 id="web-localization-push">
      <title>Automatic Localization Using Localizers ("Push"
      Localization)</title>

      <para>The central idea behind 'push' localization is that an application
      developer should be able to specify localization resources in the
      resource file for the page and have those resources automatically
      applied to the user controls on the page by the framework. For example,
      an application developer could define a page such as
      <literal>UserRegistration.aspx</literal>...</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Page language="c#" Codebehind="UserRegistration.aspx.cs"
    AutoEventWireup="false" Inherits="ArtFair.Web.UI.Forms.UserRegistration" %&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;spring:Content id="mainContent" contentPlaceholderId="main" runat="server"&gt;
            &lt;div align="right"&gt;
                &lt;asp:LinkButton ID="english" Runat="server" CommandArgument="en-US"&gt;English&lt;/asp:LinkButton&gt;&amp;nbsp;
                &lt;asp:LinkButton ID="serbian" Runat="server" CommandArgument="sr-SP-Latn"&gt;Srpski&lt;/asp:LinkButton&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;table&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:Label id="emailLabel" Runat="server"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:TextBox id="email" Runat="server" Width="150px"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:Label id="passwordLabel" Runat="server"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:TextBox id="password" Runat="server" Width="150px"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:Label id="passwordConfirmationLabel" Runat="server"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:TextBox id="passwordConfirmation" Runat="server" Width="150px"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:Label id="nameLabel" Runat="server"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;&lt;asp:TextBox id="name" Runat="server" Width="150px"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
...

                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td colspan="2"&gt;
                        &lt;asp:Button id="saveButton" Runat="server"/&gt;&amp;nbsp;
                        &lt;asp:Button id="cancelButton" Runat="server"/&gt;
                    &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/table&gt;
        &lt;/spring:Content&gt;
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>A close inspection of the above <literal>.aspx</literal> code
      reveals that none of the <classname>Label</classname> or
      <classname>Button</classname> controls have had a value assigned to the
      <literal>Text</literal> property. The values of the
      <literal>Text</literal> property for these controls are stored in the
      local resource file (of the page) using the following convention to
      identify the resource (string).</para>

      <programlisting>$this.controlId.propertyName</programlisting>

      <para>The corresponding local resource file,
      <literal>UserRegistration.aspx.resx</literal>, is shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;root&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.emailLabel.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;Email:&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.passwordLabel.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;Password:&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.passwordConfirmationLabel.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;Confirm password:&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.nameLabel.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;Full name:&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;

...

  &lt;data name="$this.countryLabel.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;Country:&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.saveButton.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;$messageSource.save&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.cancelButton.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;$messageSource.cancel&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
&lt;/root&gt;</programlisting>

      <tip>
        <title>VS2003</title>

        <para>To view the .resx file for a page, you may need to enable
        "Project/Show All Files" in Visual Studio. When "Show All Files" is
        enabled, the .resx file appears like a "child" of the code-behind
        page.</para>

        <para>When Visual Studio creates the .resx file, it will include a
        <literal>xds:schema</literal> element and several
        <literal>reshead</literal> elements. Your data elements will follow
        the <literal>reshead</literal> elements. When working with the .resx
        files, you may want to choose "Open With" from the context menu and
        select the "Source Code" text editor.</para>
      </tip>

      <tip>
        <title>VS2005</title>

        <para>To create a resource file in VS2005, open your control or page
        in design mode and select "Tools/Generate local resource" from the
        menu</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Finally a localizer must be configured for the page to enable
      automatic localization:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object id="localizer" type="Spring.Globalization.Localizers.ResourceSetLocalizer, Spring.Core"/&gt;

&lt;object type="UserRegistration.aspx"&gt;
    &lt;property name="Localizer" ref="localizer"/&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>For more information on configuring localizers see <xref
      linkend="web-localizers" /></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-globalresources">
      <title>Global Message Sources</title>

      <para>The last two resource definitions from the previous section
      require some additional explanation:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;data name="$this.saveButton.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;$messageSource.save&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data name="$this.cancelButton.Text"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;$messageSource.cancel&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>In some cases it makes sense to apply a resource that is defined
      <emphasis>globally</emphasis> as opposed to locally. In this example, it
      makes better sense to define values for the <literal>Save</literal> and
      <literal>Cancel</literal> buttons globally as they will probably be used
      throughout the application.</para>

      <para>The above example demonstrates how one can achieve that by
      defining a <emphasis>resource redirection</emphasis> expression as the
      value of a local resource by prefixing a global resource name with the
      following string.</para>

      <programlisting>$messageSource.</programlisting>

      <para>Taking the case of the above example, this will tell the localizer
      to use the <literal>save</literal> and <literal>cancel</literal>
      portions of the resource key as lookup keys to retrieve the actual
      values from a global message source. The important thing to remember is
      that one need only define a resource redirect once, typically in the
      invariant resource file  any lookup for a resource redirect will simply
      fall back to the invariant culture, and result in a global message
      source lookup using the correct culture.</para>

      <para>Global resources are (on a per-context basis) defined as a plain
      vanilla object definition using the reserved name of
      <literal>'messageSource'</literal>, which one can add to one's
      Spring.NET configuration file as shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object id="messageSource" type="Spring.Context.Support.ResourceSetMessageSource, Spring.Core"&gt;
    &lt;property name="ResourceManagers"&gt;
        &lt;list&gt;
            &lt;value&gt;MyApp.Web.Resources.Strings, MyApp.Web&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <important>
        <title>NET 2.0</title>

        <para>To use resources from your App_GlobalResources folder, specify
        <literal>App_GlobalResources</literal> as assembly name (see the
        SpringAir example application for more):</para>

        <literal>&lt;value&gt;Resources.Strings,
        App_GlobalResources&lt;/value&gt;</literal>
      </important>

      <para>The global resources are cached within the Spring.NET
      <classname>IApplicationContext</classname> and are accessible through
      the Spring.NET <literal>IMessageSource</literal> interface.</para>

      <para>The Spring.Web <literal>Page</literal> and
      <literal>UserControl</literal> classes have a reference to their owning
      <classname>IApplicationContext</classname> and it's associated
      <literal>IMessageSource</literal>. As such, they will automatically
      redirect resource lookups to a global message source if a local resource
      cannot be found.</para>

      <para>Currently, the <literal>ResourceSetMessageSource</literal> is the
      only message source implementation that ships with Spring.NET.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-localizers">
      <title>Working with Localizers</title>

      <para>In order to apply resources automatically, a localizer needs to be
      injected into all pages requiring this feature (typically accomplished
      using a base page definition that other pages will inherit from). The
      injected localizer will inspect the resource file when the page is first
      requested, cache the resources that start with the
      <literal>'$this'</literal> marker string value, and apply the values to
      the controls that populate the page prior to the page being
      rendered.</para>

      <para>A localizer is simply an object that implements the
      <classname>Spring.Globalization.ILocalizer</classname> interface.
      <classname>Spring.Globalization.AbstractLocalizer</classname> is
      provided as a convenient base class for localization: this class has one
      abstract method, <literal>LoadResources</literal>. This method must load
      and return a list of all the resources that must be automatically
      applied from the resource store.</para>

      <para>Spring.NET ships with one concrete implementation of a localizer,
      <classname>Spring.Globalization.Localizers.ResourceSetLocalizer</classname>,
      that retrieves a list of resources to apply from the local resource
      file. Future releases of Spring.NET may provide other localizers that
      read resources from an XML file or even a flat text file that contains
      resource name-value pairs which will allow application developers to
      store resources within the files in a web application instead of as
      embedded resources in an assembly. Of course, if an application
      developer would rather store such resources in a database, he or she can
      write their own <classname>ILocalizer</classname> implementation that
      will load a list of resources to apply from a database.</para>

      <para>As mentioned previously, one would typically configure the
      localizer to be used within an abstract base definition for those pages
      that require localization as shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object id="localizer" type="Spring.Globalization.Localizers.ResourceSetLocalizer, Spring.Core"/&gt;

&lt;object name="basePage" abstract="true"&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;
        Pages that reference this definition as their parent
        (see examples below) will automatically inherit following properties.
    &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;property name="Localizer" ref="localizer"/&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Of course, nothing prevents an application developer from defining
      a different localizer for each page in the application; in any case, one
      can always override the localizer defined in a base (page) definition.
      Alternatively, if one does want any resources to be applied
      automatically one can completely omit the localizer definition.</para>

      <para>One last thing to note is that Spring.NET
      <classname>UserControl</classname> instances will (by default) inherit
      the localizer and other localization settings from the page that they
      are contained within, but one can similarly also override that behavior
      using explicit dependency injection.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-pull-localization">
      <title>Applying Resources Manually ("Pull" Localization)</title>

      <para>While automatic localization as described above works great for
      many form-like pages, it doesn't work nearly as well for the controls
      defined within any iterative controls because the IDs for such iterative
      controls are not fixed. It also doesn't work well in those cases where
      one needs to display the same resource multiple times within the same
      page. For example, think of the header columns for outgoing and return
      flights tables within the SpringAir application (see <xref
      linkend="springair" />).</para>

      <para>In these situations, one should use a pull-style mechanism for
      localization, which boils down to a simple <literal>GetMessage</literal>
      call as shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;asp:Repeater id="outboundFlightList" Runat="server"&gt;
  &lt;HeaderTemplate&gt;
    &lt;table border="0" width="90%" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" align="center" class="suggestedTable"&gt;
      &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr class="suggestedTableCaption"&gt;
          &lt;th colspan="6"&gt;
            &lt;%= GetMessage("outboundFlights") %&gt;
          &lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr class="suggestedTableColnames"&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("flightNumber") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("departureDate") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("departureAirport") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("destinationAirport") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("aircraft") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;&lt;%= GetMessage("seatPlan") %&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/thead&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;/HeaderTemplate&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The <literal>GetMessage</literal> method is available within both
      the <classname>Spring.Web.UI.Page </classname> and
      <classname>Spring.Web.UI.UserControl</classname> classes, and it will
      automatically fall back to a global message source lookup if a local
      resource is not found.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-localizing-images">
      <title>Localizing Images within a Web Application</title>

      <para>Spring.Web provides an easy (and consistent) way to localize
      images within a web application. Unlike text resources, which can be
      stored within embedded resource files, XML files, or even a database,
      images in a typical web application are usually stored as files on the
      file system. Using a combination of directory naming conventions and a
      custom ASP.NET control, Spring.Web allows application developers to
      localize images within the page as easily as text resources.</para>

      <para>The Spring.Web <literal>Page</literal> class exposes the
      <literal>ImagesRoot</literal> property, which is used to define the root
      directory where images are stored. The default value is 'Images', which
      means that the localizer expects to find an 'Images' directory within
      the application root, but one can set it to any value in the definition
      of the page.</para>

      <para>In order to localize images, one needs to create a directory for
      each localized culture under the <literal>ImagesRoot</literal> directory
      as shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>/MyApp
   /Images
      /en
      /en-US
      /fr
      /fr-CA
      /sr-SP-Cyrl
      /sr-SP-Latn
      ...</programlisting>

      <para>Once an appropriate folder hierarchy is in place all one need do
      is put the localized images in the appropriate directories and make sure
      that different translations of the same image are named the same. In
      order to place a localized image on a page, one needs to use the
      <literal>&lt;spring:LocalizedImage&gt;</literal> as shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;%@ Page language="c#" Codebehind="StandardTemplate.aspx.cs"
                AutoEventWireup="false" Inherits="SpringAir.Web.StandardTemplate" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0 Transitional//EN" &gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;spring:LocalizedImage id="logoImage" imageName="spring-air-logo.jpg" borderWidth="0" runat="server" /&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>This control will find the most specific directory that contains
      an image with the specified name using standard localization fallback
      rules and the user's culture. For example, if the user's culture is
      <literal>'en-US'</literal>, the localizer will look for the
      <literal>spring-air-logo.jpg</literal> file in
      <literal>Images/en-US</literal>, then in <literal>Images/en</literal>
      and finally, if the image file has still not been found, in the root
      <literal>Images</literal> directory (which for all practical purposes
      serves as an invariant culture folder).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-culture">
      <title>User Culture Management</title>

      <para>In addition to global and local resource management, Spring.Web
      also adds support for user culture management by exposing the current
      <classname>CultureInfo</classname> through the
      <literal>UserCulture</literal> property on the
      <classname>Page</classname> and <classname>UserControl</classname>
      classes.</para>

      <para>The <literal>UserCulture</literal> property will simply delegate
      culture resolution to an implementation of
      <classname>Spring.Globalization.ICultureResolver</classname> interface.
      One can specify exactly which culture resolver to use by configuring the
      <literal>CultureResolver</literal> property of the
      <classname>Page</classname> class in the relevant object definition as
      shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object name="BasePage" abstract="true"&gt;
    &lt;property name="CultureResolver"&gt;
        &lt;object type="Spring.Globalization.Resolvers.CookieCultureResolver, Spring.Web"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Several useful implementations of
      <classname>ICultureResolver</classname> ship as part of Spring.Web, so
      it is unlikely that application developers will have to implement their
      own culture resolver. However, if one does have such a requirement, the
      resulting implementation should be fairly straightforward as there are
      only two methods that one need implement. The following sections discuss
      each available implementation of the
      <classname>ICultureResolver</classname> interface.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>DefaultWebCultureResolver</title>

        <para>This is default culture resolver implementation. It will be used
        if one does not specify a culture resolver for a page, or if one
        explicitly injects a <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname>
        into a page definition explicitly. The latter case (explicit
        injection) is sometimes useful because it allows one to specify a
        culture that should always be used by providing a value to the
        <literal>DefaultCulture</literal> property on the resolver.</para>

        <para>The <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname> will first
        look at the <literal>DefaultCulture</literal> property and return its
        value if said property value is not null. If it is null, the
        <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname> will fall back to
        request header inspection, and finally, if no
        <literal>'Accept-Lang'</literal> request headers are present it will
        return the UI culture of the currently executing thread.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>RequestCultureResolver</title>

        <para>This resolver works in a similar way to the
        <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname> with the exception
        that it always checks request headers <emphasis>first</emphasis>, and
        only then falls back to the value of the
        <literal>DefaultCulture</literal> property or the culture code of the
        current thread.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>SessionCultureResolver</title>

        <para>This resolver will look for culture information in the user's
        session and return it if it finds one. If not, it will fall back to
        the behavior of the
        <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>CookieCultureResolver</title>

        <para>This resolver will look for culture information in a cookie, and
        return it if it finds one. If not, it will fall back to the behavior
        of the <classname>DefaultWebCultureResolver</classname>.</para>

        <warning>
          <para><classname>CookieCultureResolver</classname> will not work if
          your application uses <literal>localhost</literal> as the server
          URL, which is a typical setting in a development environment.</para>

          <para>In order to work around this limitation you should use
          <classname>SessionCultureResolver</classname> during development and
          switch to <classname>CookieCultureResolver</classname> before you
          deploy the application in a production. This is easily accomplished
          in Spring.Web (simply change the config file) but is something that
          you should be aware of.</para>
        </warning>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-culture-changing">
      <title>Changing Cultures</title>

      <para>In order to be able to change the culture application developers
      will need to use one of the culture resolvers that support culture
      changes, such as <classname>SessionCultureResolver</classname> or
      <classname>CookieCultureResolver</classname>. One could also write a
      custom <classname>ICultureResolver</classname> that will persist culture
      information in a database, as part of a user's profile.</para>

      <para>Once that requirement is satisfied, all that one need do is to set
      the <literal>UserCulture</literal> property to a new
      <classname>CultureInfo</classname> object before the page is rendered.
      In the following <literal>.aspx</literal> example, there are two link
      buttons that can be used to change the user's culture. In the
      code-behind, this is all one need do to set the new culture. A code
      snippet for the code-behind file
      (<literal>UserRegistration.aspx.cs</literal>) is shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>protected override void OnInit(EventArgs e)
{
    InitializeComponent();

    this.english.Command += new CommandEventHandler(this.SetLanguage);
    this.serbian.Command += new CommandEventHandler(this.SetLanguage);

    base.OnInit(e);
}

private void SetLanguage(object sender, CommandEventArgs e)
{
    this.UserCulture = new CultureInfo((string) e.CommandArgument);
}</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-resultmapping">
    <title>Result Mapping</title>

    <para>One of the problems evident in many ASP.NET applications is that
    there is no built-in way to externalize the flow of an application. The
    most common way of defining application flow is by hardcoding calls to the
    <literal>Response.Redirect</literal> and
    <literal>Server.Transfer</literal> methods within event handlers.</para>

    <para>This approach is problematic because any changes to the flow of an
    application necessitates code changes (with the attendant recompilation,
    testing, redeployment, etc). A much better way, and one that has been
    proven to work successfully in many MVC ( <ulink
    url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnpatterns/html/DesMVC.asp">Model-View-Controller</ulink>)
    web frameworks is to provide the means to externalize the mapping of
    action results to target pages.</para>

    <para>Spring.Web adds this functionality to ASP.NET by allowing one to
    define result mappings within the definition of a page, and to then simply
    use logical result names within event handlers to control application
    flow.</para>

    <para>In Spring.Web, a logical result is encapsulated and defined by the
    <classname>Result</classname> class; because of this one can configure
    results just like any other object:</para>

    <programlisting>
&lt;objects xmlns="http://www.springframework.net"&gt;

    &lt;object id="homePageResult" type="Spring.Web.Support.Result, Spring.Web"&gt;
        &lt;property name="TargetPage" value="~/Default.aspx"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="Mode" value="Transfer"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="Parameters"&gt;
            &lt;dictionary&gt;
                &lt;entry key="literal" value="My Text"/&gt;
                &lt;entry key="name" value="%{UserInfo.FullName}"/&gt;
                &lt;entry key="host" value="%{Request.UserHostName}"/&gt;
            &lt;/dictionary&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/object&gt;

    &lt;object id="loginPageResult" type="Spring.Web.Support.Result, Spring.Web"&gt;
        &lt;property name="TargetPage" value="Login.aspx"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="Mode" value="Redirect"/&gt;
    &lt;/object&gt;

    &lt;object type="UserRegistration.aspx" parent="basePage"&gt;
        &lt;property name="UserManager" ref="userManager"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="Results"&gt;
            &lt;dictionary&gt;
                &lt;entry key="userSaved" value-ref="homePageResult"/&gt;
                &lt;entry key="cancel" value-ref="loginPageResult"/&gt;
            &lt;/dictionary&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/object&gt;

&lt;/objects&gt;
</programlisting>

    <para>The only property that you <emphasis>must</emphasis> supply a value
    for each and every result is the <literal>TargetPage</literal> property.
    The value of the <literal>Mode</literal> property can be either
    <literal>Transfer</literal>, <literal>TransferNoPreserve</literal>,
    <literal>Redirect</literal>, and defaults to <literal>Transfer</literal>
    if none is specified. TransferNoPreserve issues a server-side transfer
    with 'preserveForm=false', so that QueryString and Form data are not
    preserved.</para>

    <para>If one's target page requires parameters, one can define them using
    the <literal>Parameters</literal> dictionary property. One simply
    specifies either literal values or <link linkend="navigation">object
    navigation expressions</link> for such parameter values; if one specifies
    an expression, this expression will be evaluated in the context of the
    page in which the result is being referenced... in the specific case of
    the above example, this means that any page that uses the
    <literal>homePageResult</literal> needs to expose a
    <classname>UserInfo</classname> property on the page class itself.<note>
        <para>In Spring 1.1.0 and before the prefix used to indicate an object
        navigation expression in the <literal>Parameters</literal> dictionary
        property was the dollar sign, i.e.
        <literal>${UserInfo.FullName}.</literal>This conflicted with the
        prefix used to perform property replacement, the dollar sign, as
        described in the section <link
        linkend="objects-factory-placeholderconfigurer">PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer</link>.
        As a workaround you can change the prefix and suffix used in
        PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer to be different, for example prefix =
        $${ and suffix = }. In Spring 1.1.1 a new prefix character, the
        percent sign (i.e.<literal>%{UserInfo.FullName}</literal>.) can be
        used in the <literal>Parameters</literal> dictionary to avoid this
        conflict so you can keep the familiar NAnt style
        PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer defaults.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para>Parameters will be handled differently depending on the result mode.
    For redirect results, every parameter will be converted to a string, then
    URL encoded, and finally appended to a redirect query string. On the other
    hand, parameters for transfer results will be added to the
    <literal>HttpContext.Items</literal> collection before the request is
    transferred to the target page. This means that transfers are more
    flexible because any object can be passed as a parameter between pages.
    They are also more efficient because they don't require a round-trip to
    the client and back to the server, so transfer mode is recommended as the
    preferred result mode (it is also the current default).</para>

    <para>The above example shows independent result object definitions, which
    are useful for global results such as a home- and login- page.
    <classname>Result</classname> definitions that are only going to be used
    by one page should be simply embedded within the definition of a page,
    either as inner object definitions or using a special shortcut notation
    for defining a result definition:</para>

    <programlisting>
&lt;object type="~/UI/Forms/UserRegistration.aspx" parent="basePage"&gt;
  &lt;property name="UserManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref object="userManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  
  &lt;property name="Results"&gt;
    &lt;dictionary&gt;
      &lt;entry key="userSaved" value="redirect:UserRegistered.aspx?status=Registration Successful,user=${UserInfo}"/&gt;
      &lt;entry key="cancel" value-ref="homePageResult"/&gt;
    &lt;/dictionary&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
</programlisting>

    <para>The short notation for the result must adhere to the following
    format...</para>

    <programlisting>[&lt;mode&gt;:]&lt;targetPage&gt;[?param1,param2,...,paramN]</programlisting>

    <para>There are three possible values for the <literal>mode</literal>
    value referred to in the above notation snippet; they are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>redirect</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>transfer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TransferNoPreserve</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>They correspond to the values of the ResultMode enumeration. One
    thing to notice is that a comma is used instead of an ampersand to
    separate parameters; this is done so as to avoid the need for laborious
    ampersand escaping within an XML object definition. The use of the
    ampersand character is still supported if required, but one will then have
    to specify it using the well known &amp; entity reference.</para>

    <para>Once one has defined one's results, it is very simple to use them
    within the event handlers of one's pages
    (<literal>UserRegistration.apsx.cs</literal>)...</para>

    <programlisting>private void SaveUser(object sender, EventArgs e)
{
    UserManager.SaveUser(UserInfo);
    SetResult("userSaved");
}

public void Cancel(object sender, EventArgs e)
{
    SetResult("cancel");
}

protected override void OnInit(EventArgs e)
{
    InitializeComponent();

    this.saveButton.Click += new EventHandler(this.SaveUser);
    this.cancelButton.Click += new EventHandler(this.Cancel);

    base.OnInit(e);
}</programlisting>

    <para>One could of course further refactor the above example and use
    defined constants. This would be a good thing to do in the case of a
    logical result name such as "home" that is likely to be referenced by many
    pages.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="web-clientscripting">
    <title>Client-Side Scripting</title>

    <para>ASP.NET has decent support for client-side scripting through the use
    of the <literal>Page.RegisterClientScriptBlock</literal> and
    <literal>Page.RegisterStartupScript</literal> methods.</para>

    <para>However, neither of these two methods allows you to output a
    registered script markup within a <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section
    of a page, which is (in many cases) exactly what you would like to
    do.</para>

    <sect2 id="web-scripthead">
      <title>Registering Scripts within the head HTML section</title>

      <para>Spring.Web adds several methods to enhance client-side scripting
      to the base <classname>Spring.Web.UI.Page</classname> class:
      <literal>RegisterHeadScriptBlock</literal> and
      <literal>RegisterHeadScriptFile</literal>, each with a few overrides.
      You can call these methods from your custom pages and controls in order
      to register script blocks and script files that must be included in the
      <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section of the final HTML page.</para>

      <para>The only additional thing that is required to make this work is
      that you use the <literal>&lt;spring:Head&gt;</literal> server-side
      control to define your <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section instead
      of using the standard HTML <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> element. This
      is shown below.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;%@ Page language="c#" Codebehind="StandardTemplate.aspx.cs"
                AutoEventWireup="false" Inherits="SpringAir.Web.StandardTemplate" %&gt;
&lt;%@ Register TagPrefix="spring" Namespace="Spring.Web.UI.Controls" Assembly="Spring.Web" %&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0 Transitional//EN" &gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;spring:Head runat="server" id="Head1"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;
      &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="title" runat="server"&gt;
        &lt;%= GetMessage("default.title") %&gt;
      &lt;/spring:ContentPlaceHolder&gt;
    &lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;LINK href="&lt;%= CssRoot %&gt;/default.css" type="text/css" rel="stylesheet"&gt;
    &lt;spring:ContentPlaceHolder id="head" runat="server"&gt;&lt;/spring:ContentPlaceHolder&gt;
  &lt;/spring:Head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
  ...
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The example above shows you how you would typically set-up a
      <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section within a master page template in
      order to be able to change the title value and to add additional
      elements to the <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section from the child
      pages using <literal>&lt;spring:ContentPlaceholder&gt;</literal>
      controls. However, only the <literal>&lt;spring:Head&gt;</literal>
      declaration is required in order for Spring.NET
      <literal>Register*</literal> scripts to work properly.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-scriptcss">
      <title>Adding CSS Definitions to the head Section</title>

      <para>In a similar fashion, you can add references to CSS files, or even
      specific styles, directly to the <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> HTML
      section using <literal>Page.RegisterStyle</literal> and
      <literal>Page.RegisterStyleFile</literal> methods. The latter one simply
      allows you to include a reference to an external CSS file, while the
      former one allows you to define embedded style definitions by specifying
      the style name and definition as the parameters. The final list of style
      definitions registered this way will be rendered within the single
      embedded <literal>style</literal> section of the final HTML
      document.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="web-wellknowdirectory">
      <title>Well-Known Directories</title>

      <para>In order to make the manual inclusion of client-side scripts, CSS
      files and images easier, the Spring.Web <literal>Page</literal> class
      exposes several properties that help you reference such artifacts using
      absolute paths. This affords web application developers a great deal of
      convenience functionality straight out of the box if they stick to
      common conventions such as a web application (directory)
      structure..</para>

      <para>These properties are <literal>ScriptsRoot</literal>,
      <literal>CssRoot</literal> and <literal>ImagesRoot</literal>. They have
      default values of <literal>Scripts</literal>, <literal>CSS</literal> and
      <literal>Images</literal>, which will work just fine if you create and
      use these directories in your web application root. However, if you
      prefer to place them somewhere else, you can always override default
      values by injecting new values into your page definitions (you will
      typically inject these values only in the base page definition, as they
      are normally shared by all the pages in the application). An example of
      such configuration is shown below:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;object name="basePage" abstract="true"&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;
        Convenience base page definition for all the pages.

        Pages that reference this definition as their parent (see the examples below)
        will automatically inherit the following properties....

    &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;property name="CssRoot" value="Web/CSS"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="ImagesRoot" value="Web/Images"/&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Spring User Controls</title>

    <para>Spring provides several custom user controls that are located in the
    <literal>Spring.Web.UI.Controls</literal> namespace. This section
    primarily lists the controls and points to other documentation to provide
    additional information. There are a few other controls not documented
    here, please check the SDK docs for their descriptions.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Validation Controls</title>

      <para>The location in the web page where validation errors are to be
      rendered can be specifies by using the
      <classname>ValidationSummary</classname> and
      <classname>ValidationError</classname> controls. There are two controls
      since they have different defaults for how errors are rendered.
      <classname>ValidationSummary</classname> is used to display potentially
      multiple errors identified by the validation framework.
      <classname>ValidationError</classname> is used to display field-level
      validation errors. Please refer to the section <link
      linkend="validation-aspnet-usage">ASP.NET usage tips</link> in the
      chapter on the <link linkend="validation">Validation Framework</link>
      more information.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Databinding Controls</title>

      <para>Some standard controls are not easy to use with Spring's
      databinding support. Examples are check boxes and ratio button groups.
      In this case you should use the <classname>CheckBoxList</classname> and
      <classname>RadioButtonGroup</classname> controls. Databinding itself can
      be done using the <link
      linkend="web-databindingpanel">DataBindingPanel</link> instead of the
      using the BindingManager API within the code behind page.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Calendar Control</title>

      <para>A pop-up DHTML calendar control is provided. It is a slightly
      modified version of the <ulink
      url="http://www.dynarch.com/projects/calendar">Dynarch.com DHTML
      Calendar</ulink> control written by Mihai Bazon.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Panel Control</title>

      <para>You can suppress dependency injection for controls inside your
      ASP.NET by using the Panel control. See the section <link
      linkend="web-panel-control-di">Customizing control dependency
      injection</link> for more information.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>